Allen Polite Papers 2010.0117
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Allen Polite Papers
1955-1993.
2010.0117
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
10.5 Linear feet
Handwritten manuscripts, notebooks, letters, typed transcriptions of poetry, prose and a play for voices, and published works by Allen Polite, writer and artist affiliated with the Black Arts Movement.
Polite, Allen, 1932-1993.
Biography
Writer and artist Allen Polite (1932-1993) was born in Newark, NJ. He was raised and went to school there until he was drafted into the United States Army. He served in Korea and Japan in 1952 and 1953. Polite settled in Greenwich Village, and between 1954 and 1956, studied philosophy at Columbia University. After 1958, he worked at the United Nations headquarters in New York. The writer LeRoi Jones acknowledged Polite as his 'mentor' in his Autobiography and first published Polite's poetry in 1958 in the magazine Yugen. In the early 1960s Polite worked on a novel (never completed) and a long cycle of poetry and prose called "The Dead Seeds," but he refused to publish his work. Polite's writing was included in Sixes and Sevens, An Anthology of New Poetry (Paul Breman, London, 1962), and Langston Hughes' New Negro Poets, U.S.A. published in 1964. Carlene Hatcher Polite in her first novel The Flagellants, published initially in France in 1966, featured the relationship of a young couple that is partially based on her relationship with Allen Polite.
In 1963 Polite left New York for Paris, London, and Stockholm, where he visited his friend the artist Harvey Cropper. He decided to settle in Stockholm, where he joined an international group of artists which centered on a number of black Americans already resident there. Polite began drawing and painting in addition to his writing, and in 1964 he organized and sponsored the exhibition "10 American Negro Artists Living and Working in Europe" at Den Frie, the largest gallery in Copenhagen. To support himself, Polite took a job as a clerk at CWZ Grafiska AB, a company that supplied material for the graphic industry, and subsequently gained the position of head buyer for bookbinding material. In Sweden he met Helene Etzelsdorfer who remained his companion, and later his wife, from 1963 until his death from cancer in 1993. She prepared Allen's work for publication and privately published three volumes including Poems (1996), The Rice and Fiol of the Turd Rake (1996), a 'rhapsodic play for three voices', and Looka Here, Now! (1997), poems from the 1950s.
General note
Published Works:
Scope and Content
The collection contains handwritten manuscripts by Allen Polite of poetry, prose, aphorisms, dialogues, songs and a play for voices; early writing and student work; notebooks including drafts and notes; transcriptions of poetry by Helene Polite; published works, and a self-portrait in watercolor.
Arrangement
Handwritten manuscripts and notebooks are filed with typed transcriptions by Helene Polite. Titles for individual texts are linked in this inventory to their location in the collection, and additionally, are filed in hardcopy with their associated manuscripts.
Series I: Box Inventory ( 1955-1993 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of literary manuscript materials. Contact the Curator or ask at the reference desk.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated by Helene Polite in September 2010, with the generous assistance of Samuel and Ann Charters.
African American authors--United States.; African American poets--United States.; Artwork.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Notes.; Photographs.; Publications.; Sketches.
- Series I: Box Inventory, 1955-1993
  - Family letters and student work, circa 1955-1958 (Box 1:, Folder 1-3)
  - Manuscripts (uncataloged), undated (Box 1:, Folder 4-9)
  - Postcard ( LeRoi Jones) and personal documents, undated, 1958 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - undated (Box 2:, Folder 11-14)
  - Typed transcriptions [Reference: Binder 1B], undated (Box 2:, Folder 15-18)
  - 1959, 1964 (Box 2:, Folder 19-20)
  - 1966 (Box 3:, Folder 21-22)
  - Typed transcriptions [Reference: Binder 2B], undated (Box 3:, Folder 23-25)
  - undated (Box 3:, Folder 26-29)
  - Typed transcriptions [Reference: Binder 3B], undated (Box 4:, Folder 30-33)
  - undated (Box 4:, Folder 34-36)
  - Typed transcriptions [Reference: Binder 4B], undated (Box 4:, Folder 37-38)
  - Typed transcriptions [Reference: Binder 4B], undated (Box 5:, Folder 39-40)
  - undated (Box 5:, Folder 41-42)
  - Typed transcriptions [Reference: Binder 5B], undated (Box 5:, Folder 43-45)
  - undated (Box 6:, Folder 46-49)
  - Typed transcriptions [Reference: Binder 6B], undated (Box 6:, Folder 50-54)
  - Materials chosen for 'The Dead Seeds' with copious notations by several different readers (no manuscript materials included). [Reference: Binder 8A], undated (Box 6:, Folder 55-57)
  - Materials chosen for 'The Dead Seeds' with copious notations by several different readers (no manuscript materials included). [Reference: Binder 8A], undated (Box 7:, Folder 58-61)
  - Final draft of 'The Dead Seeds' (poems selected by Helene Polite from various manuscripts and transcriptions). [Reference: Typescript 8B], undated (Box 7:, Folder 62-65)